<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Abstract syntax tree access</title>

  <section>
    <title>Tutorial on Abstract Syntax Trees (ASTs)</title>

    <section>
      <title>About Abstract Syntax Trees</title>

      <para>A fundamental data structure in most compilers is the Abstract
      Syntax Tree (AST). An AST serves as an abstract representation of a
      computer program and is often used in a compiler to perform analyses
      (e.g., binding names to declarations and checking type correctness of a
      program) and as a basis for code generation.</para>

      <para>Three different ASTs are used in the JModelica.org
      front-ends.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis>source AST</emphasis> results from parsing of
          the Modelica or Optimica source code. This AST shares the structure
          of the source code, and consists of a hierarchy consisting of Java
          objects corresponding to class and component declarations, equations
          and algorithms. The source AST can also be used for unparsing, i.e.,
          pretty printing of the source code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis>instance AST</emphasis> represents a particular
          model instance. Typically, the user selects a class to instantiate,
          and the compiler then computes the corresponding instance AST. The
          instance AST differs from the source AST in that in the former case,
          all components are expanded down to variables of primitive type. An
          important feature of the instance AST is that it is used to
          represent modification environments; merging of modifications takes
          place in the instance AST. As a consequence, all analysis, such as
          name and type analysis takes is done based on the instance
          AST.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis>flat AST</emphasis> represents the flat Modelica
          model. Once the instance AST has been computed, the flat AST is
          computed simply by traversing the instance AST and collecting all
          variables of primitive type, all equations and all algorithms. The
          flat AST is then used, after some transformations, as a basis for
          code generation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For more information on how the JModelica.org compiler transforms
      these ASTs, see the paper "Implementation of a Modelica compiler using
      JastAdd attribute grammars" by J.Åkesson et. al.</para>

      <para>This tutorial demonstrates how the Python interface to the three
      different ASTs in the compiler can be used. The JPype package is used to
      create Java objects in a Java Virtual Machine which is seamlessly
      integrated with the Python shell. The Java objects can be accessed
      interactively and methods of the object can be invoked.</para>

      <para>For more information about the Java classes and their methods used
      in this example, please consult the API documentation for the Modelica
      compiler. Note however that the documentation for the compiler
      front-ends is still very rudimentary. Also, the interfaces to the source
      and instance AST will be made more user friendly in upcoming
      versions.</para>

      <para>Three different usages of ASTs are shown:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Count the number of classes in the Modelica standard library.
          In this example, a Python function is defined to traverse the source
          AST which results from parsing of the Modelica standard
          library.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Instantiate the CauerLowPassAnalog model. The instance AST for
          this model is dumped and it is demonstrated how the merged
          modification environments can be accessed. Also, it is shown how a
          component redeclaration affects the instance tree.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Flatten the CauerLowPassAnalog model instance and print some
          statistics of the flattened Model.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Python commands in this tutorial may be copied and pasted
      directly into a Python shell, in some cases with minor modifications.
      You are, however, strongly encouraged to copy the commands into a text
      file, e.g., <filename>ast_example.py</filename>.</para>

      <para>Start the tutorial by creating a working directory and copy the
      file
      <filename>$JMODELICA_HOME/Python/pyjmi/examples/files/CauerLowPassAnalog.mo</filename>
      to your working directory. An on-line version of <filename
      xlink:href=""><link
      xlink:href="https://svn.jmodelica.org/trunk/Python/src/pyjmi/examples/files/CauerLowPassAnalog.mo">CauerLowPassAnalog.mo</link></filename>
      is also available (depending on which browser you use, you may have to
      accept the site certificate by clicking through a few steps). If you
      choose to create Python script file, save it to the working directory.
      The tutorial is based on a model from the Modelica Standard Library:
      <literal>Modelica.Electrical.Analog.Basic.Examples.CauerLowPassAnalog</literal>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Load the Modelica standard library</title>

      <para>Before we can start working with the ASTs, we need to import the
      Python packages that will be used</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Import library for path manipulations
import os.path

# Import the JModelica.org Python packages
import pymodelica
from pymodelica.compiler_wrappers import ModelicaCompiler

# Import numerical libraries
import numpy as N
import ctypes as ct
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt

# Import JPype
import jpype

# Create a reference to the java package 'org'
org = jpype.JPackage('org')
</programlisting>

      <para>Also, we need to create an instance of a Modelica compiler in
      order to compile models:</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Create a compiler and compiler target object
mc = ModelicaCompiler()

# Build trees as if for an FMU for ME v 1.0
target = mc.create_target_object("me", "1.0")
</programlisting>

      <para>In order to avoid parsing the same file multiple times (we will
      not change the Modelica file in this tutorial), we will check the
      variable <literal>source_root</literal> exists in the shell before we
      parse the file <filename>CauerLowPassAnalog.mo</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Don't parse the file if it has already been parsed.
try:
    source_root.getProgramRoot()
except:
    # Parse the file CauerLowPassAnalog.mo and get the root node
    # of the source AST
    source_root = mc.parse_model("CauerLowPassAnalog.mo")
</programlisting>

      <para>At this point, try the built-in help feature of Python by typing
      the following command in the shell to see the help text for the function
      you just used.</para>

      <programlisting language="python">In [2]: help(mc.parse_model)
</programlisting>

      <para>In the first part of the tutorial, we will not work with the
      filter model, but rather load the Modelica standard library. Again, we
      check if the library has already been loaded:</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Don't load the standard library if it is already loaded
try:
    modelica.getName().getID()
except NameError, e:
    # Load the Modelica standard library and get the class
    # declaration AST node corresponding to the Modelica
    # package.
    modelica = source_root.getProgram().getLibNode(0). \
               getStoredDefinition().getElement(0)
</programlisting>

      <para>The means to access the node in the source AST corresponding to
      the class (package) declaration of the Modelica library is somewhat
      cumbersome; the source AST interface will be improved in later
      versions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Count the number of classes in the Modelica standard
      library</title>

      <para>Having accessed a node in the source AST, we may now perform
      analysis by traversing the tree. Say that we are interested in counting
      the number of classes (packages, models, blocks, functions etc.) in the
      Modelica standard library. As the basis for traversing the AST, we may
      use the method <literal>ClassDecl.classes()</literal> that returns an
      iterator over local classes contained in a class. Based on this method,
      a Python function for traversing the class hierarchy of the source AST
      can be defined:</para>

      <programlisting language="python">def count_classes(class_decl,depth):
    """ Count the number of classes hierarchically contained
    in a class declaration."""
    # Get an iterator over of local classes using the method ClassDecl.classes()
    # which returns a Java Iterable object over ClassDecl objects.
    local_classes = class_decl.classes().iterator()
       
    num_classes = 0
    # Loop over all local classes
    while local_classes.hasNext():
        # Call count_classes recursively for all local classes 
        # (including the contained class itself)
        num_classes += 1 + count_classes(local_classes.next(), depth + 1)

    # If the class declaration corresponds to a package, print
    # the number of hierarchically contained classes
    if class_decl.isPackage() and depth &lt;= 1:
        print("The package %s has %d hierachically contained classes" \
              %(class_decl.qualifiedName(),num_classes))
            
    # Return the number of hierachically contained classes
    return num_classes
</programlisting>

      <para>We then call the function:</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Call count_classes for 'Modelica'
num_classes = count_classes(modelica,0)
</programlisting>

      <para>Now run the script and study the printouts in the Python shell.
      The first time the script is run, you will see printouts corresponding
      also to the compiler accessing individual files of the Modelica standard
      library; the loading of the library is done on demand as the library
      classes are actually accessed. Run the script once again (using the '-i'
      switch), to get a cleaner output, which should now look similar
      to:</para>

      <programlisting>The package Modelica.UsersGuide has 39 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Blocks has 343 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.ComplexBlocks has 44 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.StateGraph has 66 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Electrical has 992 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Magnetic has 174 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Mechanics has 558 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Fluid has 687 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Media has 1791 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Thermal has 95 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Math has 166 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.ComplexMath has 31 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Utilities has 97 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Constants has 0 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.Icons has 32 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica.SIunits has 584 hierachically contained classes
The package Modelica has 5715 hierachically contained classes
</programlisting>

      <para>Take some time to ponder the results and make sure that you
      understand how the Python function <literal>count_classes</literal>
      works and which Python variables corresponds to references into the
      source AST.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dump the instance AST</title>

      <para>We shall now turn our attention to the CauerLowPassAnalog model.
      Specifically, we would like to analyze the instance hierarchy of the
      model by dumping the tree structure to the Python shell. In addition, we
      will look at the merged modification environment of each instance AST
      node. Again, we will use methods defined for the Java objects
      representing the AST.</para>

      <para>First we create an instance of the CauerLowPassAnalog filter.
      Again we only create the instance if it has not already been
      created:</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Don't instantiate if instance has been computed already
try:
    filter_instance.components()
except:
    # Retrieve the node in the instance tree corresponding to the class
    # Modelica.Electrical.Analog.Examples.CauerLowPassAnalog
    filter_instance = mc.instantiate_model(source_root,"CauerLowPassAnalog", target)
</programlisting>

      <para>Next we define a Python function for traversing the instance AST
      and printing each node in the shell. We also print the merged
      modification environment for each instance node. In order to traverse
      the AST, we use the methods
      <literal>InstNode.instComponentDeclList()</literal> and
      <literal>InstNode.instExtendsList()</literal>, which both return an
      object of the class <literal>List</literal>, which in turn contain
      instantiated component declarations and instantiated extends clauses. By
      invoking the <literal>dump_inst_ast</literal> function recursively for
      each element in these lists, the instance AST is in effect traversed.
      Due to the internal representation of the instance AST, nodes of type
      <literal>InstPrimitive</literal>, corresponding to primitive variables,
      are not leaves in the AST as would be expected. To overcome this
      complication, we simply check if a node is of type
      <literal>InstPrimitive</literal>, and if this is the case, the recursion
      stops.</para>

      <para>The environment of an instance node is accessed by calling the
      method <literal>InstNode.getMergedEnvrionment()</literal>, which returns
      a list of modifications. According to the Modelica specification, outer
      modifications overrides inner modifications, and accordingly,
      modifications in the beginning of the list has precedence over later
      modifications.</para>

      <programlisting language="python">def dump_inst_ast(inst_node, indent):
    """Pretty print an instance node, including its merged enviroment."""
    
    # Get the merged environment of an instance node
    env = inst_node.getMergedEnvironment()

    # Create a string containing the type and name of the instance node
    str = indent + inst_node.prettyPrint("")
    str = str + " {"

    # Loop over all elements in the merged modification environment
    for i in range(env.size()):
        str = str + env.get(i).toString()
        if i&lt;env.size()-1:
            str = str + ", "
        str = str + "}"

    # Print
    print(str)

    # Get all components and dump them recursively
    components = inst_node.instComponentDeclList
    
    for i in range(components.getNumChild()):
        # Assume that primitive variables are leafs in the instance AST
        if (inst_node.getClass() is \
            org.jmodelica.modelica.compiler.InstPrimitive) is False:
            dump_inst_ast(components.getChild(i),indent + "  ")

    # Get all extends clauses and dump them recursively    
    extends= inst_node.instExtendsList
    for i in range(extends.getNumChild()):
        # Assume that primitive variables are leafs in the instance AST
        if (inst_node.getClass() is \
            org.jmodelica.modelica.compiler.InstPrimitive) is False:
            dump_inst_ast(extends.getChild(i),indent + "  ")
</programlisting>

      <para>Take a minute and make sure that you understand the essential
      parts of the function.</para>

      <para>Having defined the function <literal>dump_inst_ast</literal>, we
      call it with the CauerLowPassAnalog instance as an argument.</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Dump the filter instance
dump_inst_ast(filter_instance,"")
</programlisting>

      <para>You should now see a rather lengthy printout in your shell window.
      Let us have a closer look at a few of the instances in the model. First
      look at the printouts for a resistor in the model:</para>

      <programlisting>    InstComposite: Modelica.Electrical.Analog.Basic.Resistor R1 {R=1}
      InstPrimitive: SI.Resistance R {=1, start=1, final quantity="Resistance", \
                                      final unit="Ohm"}
      InstExtends: Interfaces.OnePort {R=1}
        InstPrimitive: SI.Voltage v {final quantity="ElectricPotential", final unit="V"}
        InstPrimitive: SI.Current i {final quantity="ElectricCurrent", final unit="A"}
        InstComposite: PositivePin p {}
          InstPrimitive: SI.Voltage v {final quantity="ElectricPotential", final unit="V"}
          InstPrimitive: SI.Current i {final quantity="ElectricCurrent", final unit="A"}
        InstComposite: NegativePin n {}
          InstPrimitive: SI.Voltage v {final quantity="ElectricPotential", final unit="V"}
          InstPrimitive: SI.Current i {final quantity="ElectricCurrent", final unit="A"}
</programlisting>

      <para>The model instance if of type <literal>InstComposite</literal>,
      and contains two elements, one primitive variable, <literal>R</literal>,
      and one extends clause. The modification environment for the resistor
      contains a value modification '=1' and some modifications of the built
      in attributes for the type Real. The <literal>InstExtends</literal> node
      contains a number of child nodes, which corresponds to the content of
      the class <literal>Interfaces.OnePort</literal>. Notice the difference
      between the source AST, where an extends node is essentially a leaf in
      the tree, whereas in the instance tree, the extends clause is
      expanded.</para>

      <para>Let us have a look at the effects of redeclarations in the
      instance AST. In the CauerLowPassAnalog model, a step voltage signal
      source is used, which in turn relies on redeclaration of a generic
      signal source to a step. The instance node for the step voltage source
      <emphasis>V</emphasis> is given below:</para>

      <programlisting>    InstComposite: Modelica.Electrical.Analog.Sources.StepVoltage V {V=0, startTime=1, \
                                                                     offset=0}
      InstPrimitive: SI.Voltage V {=0, start=1, final quantity="ElectricPotential", \
                                   final unit="V"}
      InstExtends: Interfaces.VoltageSource {V=0, startTime=1, offset=0, 
           redeclare Modelica.Blocks.Sources.Step signalSource(height=V)}
        InstPrimitive: SI.Voltage offset {=0, =0, final quantity="ElectricPotential", \
                                          final unit="V"}
        InstPrimitive: SI.Time startTime {=1, =0, final quantity="Time", final unit="s"}
        InstReplacingComposite: Modelica.Blocks.Sources.Step signalSource {height=V, \
                                          final offset=offset, final startTime=startTime}
          InstPrimitive: Real height {=V, =1}
          InstExtends: Interfaces.SignalSource {height=V, final offset=offset, \
                                                final startTime=startTime}
            InstPrimitive: Real offset {=offset, =0}
            InstPrimitive: SIunits.Time startTime {=startTime, =0, final quantity="Time", \
                                                   final unit="s"}
            InstExtends: SO {height=V, final offset=offset, final startTime=startTime}
              InstPrimitive: RealOutput y {}
              InstExtends: BlockIcon {height=V, final offset=offset, 
                                      final startTime=startTime}
</programlisting>

      <para>Here we see how the modification <emphasis>redeclare
      Modelica.Blocks.Sources.Step signalSource(height=V)</emphasis> affects
      the instance AST. The node <literal>InstReplacingComposite</literal>
      represents the component instance, instantiated from the class
      <literal>Modelica.Blocks.Sources.Step</literal>, resulting from the
      redeclaration. As a consequence, this branch of the instance AST is
      significantly altered by the redeclare modification.</para>

      <para>Now look at the modification environment for the component
      instance <literal>startTime</literal>. The environment contains two
      value modifications: '=1' and '=0'. As noted above, the first
      modification in the list corresponds to the outermost modification and
      have precedence over the following modifications. Take a minute to
      figure out the origin of the modifications by looking upwards in the
      instance AST.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Flattening of the filter model</title>

      <para>Having computed the instance, we can now flatten the model:</para>

      <programlisting language="python"># Don't flatten model if it already exists
try:
    filter_flat_model.name()
except:
    # Flatten the model instance filter_instance
    filter_flat_model = mc.flatten_model(filter_instance, target)
</programlisting>

      <para>During flattening, the instance tree is traversed and all
      primitive declarations and equations are collected. In addition, such as
      scalarization and elimination of alias variables are performed.</para>

      <para>Let us have a look at the flattened model:</para>

      <programlisting language="python">print(filter_flat_model)
</programlisting>

      <para>We may also retrieve some model statistics:</para>

      <programlisting language="python">print("*** Model statistics for CauerLowPassAnalog *** ")
print("Number of differentiated variables: %d" \
       % filter_flat_model.numDifferentiatedRealVariables())
print("Number of algebraic variables:      %d" \
       % filter_flat_model.numAlgebraicContinousRealVariables())
print("Number of equations:                %d" \
       % filter_flat_model.numEquations())
print("Number of initial equations:        %d" \
       % filter_flat_model.numInitialEquations())
</programlisting>

      <para>How many variables and equations is the model composed of? Does
      the model seem to be well posed?</para>

      <para>At this point, take some time to explore the
      <literal>filter_flat_model</literal> object by typing
      'filter_flat_model.&lt;tab&gt;' in the Python shell to see what methods
      are available. You may also have a look in the Modelica compiler
      API.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
